[Music]
good good
I hope you are having a beautiful
week start is monday it's cold
but coffee by means of one enters
heat and tomatoes or mates too and
we have another new edition of
'cover meetings and finally after
from a lot of time let's start
some programming ladies and gentlemen
finally as if this subject will be shot but
well it will be hour past hour
totally the panorama but well now
yes we are already with this yes totally already
it was time to start the rule so
well how do you want to put the lay
busy for let's go fast anymore we're not going to
take more time people are anxious
from a long time ago before
it will start so the slide
Say thanks
terrific good for those who know me
and for whom not my name today is
villarreal bertoldi tell me joey this
I work as a technical leader in
mercadolibre and I am a co-founder of the
developer community
Argentina this part must have been
heard ten times some people
but it does not matter
and today we are going to be talking about good
you practice a solid code in small
word habits to talk about
solo principles by roberts and
Martin a few years ago and who are
part of a talking tool
essential in software engineering
many times we find code
that we say there has to be some
way to write this a little bit better more
maintainable cuter and the idea of ​​these
principles is that beyond what
paradigm although it is focused on
object oriented paradigm more
beyond that language because we wanted
to program this the idea is this
organize and agree a certain language
common to spot opportunities
improvement and with that start working yes
alright this
this is the first time we are going to do
a live of a programming theme like this
that mechanics is going to be can go
asking questions in chat
My friend is going to be where a hand
coordinating with that and we will be seeing
comments and things we can go
chatting feel free to comment what
you like the topic if there is us
understanding I am going to stick a
look every now and then to see this if
it is necessary to repeat some concept what
sea
this talk will be recorded in
youtube anyway this
and in periscope for those who are nothing
watching on twitter so I don't know
worry because that's why we're going
slowly cautiously calm to go
looking at each of these concepts
the first thing we need to know about this
subject is
that there are little mice in our code
and ladies and gentlemen there are little mice in
our code and they have the name of
root code which basically comes to blair
of certain code that like expression
of English than one of my friends who
is connected is going to challenge me for how
pronounce serve pronounce well code rap
this one that basically talks about the
literal translation in Spanish would
rotten code what is it
when an app turns look
how poetic this description there is a
purulent mass of code that
developers there is a gap
requires that's the and then they find
increasingly difficult to maintain because
many things happen in a large project
scale especially when this one there
lots of people working on that
draft
some of these things for example
focuses on these four concepts that
the more than one more than one person are
is asking what we do talking about
viscosity in the code I swear it's
a term that is correct and that exists
It is
there are four symptoms that determine that
the code is in a situation of
help I need help and I need you to
solve these problems
this rigidity fragility immobility and
viscosity let's go one by one
writing what it is and how else or
the less we can begin to detect them
on the stiff side we have this
that a minor change implies a
complete system rebuild
imagine for example we have a
login screen is where the user
and password the user of a field
numerical this all validations of
database were for them to just
numerical and suddenly we have to
support email addresses
electronic
tremendous problem we have because it involves
that we have to rebuild from end to end
tip the registration system
users to support such a change
because because the implementation that
initial we did was too
restrictive
so well first problem that
we have stiffness comes from the side of the
coupling also in that sense
we couple code we copy
functionalities and this we start to have
these allow a minor change
as the description says there implies a
complete system rebuild
fragility refers to what
suppose by following this example
the login suddenly these changes
start to affect things that nothing that
see suppose our application
supports comments and for some reason
we had done something to do
that how the name of the
affected user as shown in
the in the comments of our
application and that then this question
of fragility has to do with how
changes in a module start to start
to affect the behavior of others
unrelated modules
it's like an expansion effect
of expansive or a repeat effect like
when we throw a pebble in the water
those repercussions begin to impact
throughout the system module by module
if we wish our modules well the
idea is that
we can keep them completely
insulated with minimal connections
indispensable so they can
communicate but not because we change
something that has nothing to do with other
thing there should be involvement for that
it seems obvious what I'm saying but
the amount of times is impressive
what happens we fall into this problem and
generates headaches that mother
I leave mine
we have the question of immobility
internal components of a module that does not
we can extract and reuse in new
environments
this is the axiom if you want which
It is the problem that many times gives
source a component library
imagine we made an application a
combat bunch for example a
registration form we did all the
components of data fields that
require that form directly
imagine that we are for example with
react by throwing an example or having
with a range app can these
things apply to any any
it's technological that's why I start shooting
names to be made
an idea
we design our components we have
a back end that feeds them and we couple
everything in such a way that if we have to
reuse that registration form in
another part in another application or even
elsewhere in the same app
the fastest solution we can think of
it's copy and paste the code because it's
everything so intertwined so coupled
we return to this concept of
coupling it's impossible to remove it
hence reuse it
in most frameworks and ibai
in which we are working
currently and in other web technologies
there is a lot of talk about this
immobility action components is
something that prevents us from component
hoist correctly then when
we begin to face this symptom
is that some design-level decision
generated a problem and that this is going to
prevent after this movement of
components we need
and this and this viscosity factor
which sounds a little disgusting when I
we say it sounds like the code is
thickened like this everything fierce has to do with
what to compile and test for
testing a change is difficult and takes time
long time in simple change is expensive
and involves modifying multiple yogurts or
covers
with all this fashion that we also have
of the same services the micro
front-end if everything micro
t
and this has to do also for example
on the web you see a lot with the packages in
rpm if you ever noticed what's up
behind an urged pm they will see that
there are 20,000 packages installed for
do
I don't know to install the first ones
necessary components for a framework
or a super basic device library
we went so far with the
modularization of things that up
there are packages that make one that
fulfills the function of is negative and is
nano and integrates with things that
that one stays thinking because we have
packages for functions is in
petite discussion aside for everything
a whole an encounter that in itself
probably but this when we have
have to make changes on multiple layers and
all these layers exist in different
projects is a problem because we have
that for example to be compiling the
dependencies interdependencies walk
linking components to see for
do an end-to-end test and that
translates into wasting time a lot
time especially if they are projects
big
so there the importance of seeing how
we can do to make scalability
of the project and the number of modules
that we work
are simple enough for
we can have a lot if necessary but
that at the same time we can
have a way to test them out
fast without having to replicate all this
super complex structure
this paradigm comes to our rescue
of principles called soles
solid comes is an acronym like those
colored cubes will denote a
little while representing five principles
different that we are going to be touring
throughout this talk
remember that if any little thing is not left
clear if they want us to see some
example something do nothing but
throw the comment by sat at me that
It will be where I send to help me
so I miss one and we do some
example like to see what it's about
this well
solid means
single main responsability this is
in the s the principle of unique
responsibility
open closed principal at the beginning
open closed
on the main exhaust station ls or
disc replacement principle
in laws interfax serguéi are main
or a principle of segregation of
interfaces and finally dependency
main investment for the law
inversion principle of losing
depends on dependencies
we will make a brief review of each
one of these concepts before entering
in detail
sir responsible for principal
principle of sole responsibility
means that our function class or
equivalent structure containing
code has to do one and only
one thing
imagine we have a function that
already responsibilities
generate an invoice generate an invoice
has a lot of parts generate the
letterhead generate
the detail of each of each line of the
invoice post taxes do the
sum of your totals apply discounts
apply surcharges and calculate the total
generate the impression send it and others
imagine for a second what to do
things fast and because it was to see
how it almost always happens in this industry
we put all that code in a super
archi mega function thousand lines
code that magic absolutely does
everything
what is the problem we have with that
you have to read and keep my lines
code in the same file
and if we want to reuse things for
example if tomorrow I have to
generate another type of billing or
documentation they share some level
some of that data we have a
problem because everything is coupled to the
invoice generation for example
so we look we look for the way
that our container structures of
codes be as specific
specific and small possible
open clouds open closed has to
do with how we handle the
code extensibility
open cloud for example talks about how a
time the code was written and given
for productive that code cannot be
Modify
means open for extension
closed for modification because because
if we start modifying code
that we already consider productive or that
it's designed it's already implemented
it's already working
we cannot guarantee that it maintains the
same functionality
instead if we think that each
code iteration is a kind of
additive function in which we are going
adding and extending functionality
we can preserve that functionality
core of whatever we are
working is going to keep up over time
because we are not changing
behaviors but we're
adding or extending
broom replacement principle to
broad outlines speaks of when
we start to work
with multiple or multiple types
variations of the same kind of thing
let's imagine two figures
if we use a function that has a
more general abstraction of each of
the kinds of geometric shapes out there
it doesn't matter what interface or what kind of
variation let's move on to that function
should answer exactly for all
same
because the base behavior for more
that each interface can implement
particularities in abstraction more
general is the same
adding and feel interfaces has to
do with this
what happens when we offer many more
options to the person who is going to
implement a class or it's going to
use a class that has to
really use this happens a lot
when we extend objects we extend
from the first abstraction that we have to
hand because we saw two methods that we
serve for example
and suddenly we want this
use yes
there we can repeat the I repeat
in a short while liskov this segregation of
interfaces has to do with this the
concept of how do we make it
reopen this like for what like
happens with an interface when we offer
too many methods because we wanted
using two or three methods happens when
we extend from very basic classes that
offer a lot of things and we want
do a specific implementation it
we will see examples well
concrete code of each of these
things
and finally we have this
dependency investment that one of the
things it encompasses is injection of
dependencies that basically works and
has to do with how we handle
abstractions and we reuse them and the
we share we are going to go now we are going to
start delving into each of
these points to review this well
in detail how are we doing
alright let's talk about senna s
main responsability of then and
we are going to
keep this image the fact of
because you can doesn't mean you should
see what happens to that swiss army knife
with its 20 million gadgets and it's
something else is what I was saying about
billing example a while ago
because we put everything in the same unit
of codes and we can do several
a class we say should have only one
reason to mutate is to say a single reason
so that its state changes or so that
run things in this sense all kinds
or similar structure in the code by
that has to do only one thing yes
any behavior functionality
that we determine that this
code container structure call it
class call it function or whatever
call it code routine in general should
associate with the same purpose
and that purpose has to be what
concrete enough also because
we can also say an example of the
application I want to make a cart of
good shopping but a shopping cart
it has a lot of implications not
we can't it would be nice to think that
we can put all that in one
code structure well
when we talk about what a class has
than having behaviors that are associated
to the same purpose
we talked about it must have cohesion and
precisely what we want is to indicate
that there can be multiple methods
multiple properties in which
you can go working and adding
behavior as long as you follow
this mother rule of must associate a
same purpose
when the purpose of the class is
meets in that sense they can mutate one or
multiple members and this is expected
because although they can mutate more and
change various components of the state of
the structure we are with
working
mutate for the same reason which is the
purpose for which we are designing
This object
we are going to open cloud print second which is
one of the most complicated out there
a class should be open to be
extended
that is, if we define a
behavior enough
general we can allow people
who implement and use these classes
that we design to add behavior to
through extensions extensions or
that extension can be given either by
inheritance or composition does not come the
case the strategy
but if it is important that in the design and
let's talk a lot about this design
of the solution
add functionality to
as new requirements arise
if we design such a class
way we limit the universe of
action you have we risk
that when we drop a new
request
let's have some sort of problem
that prevents us from working neatly
because we are limiting
the universe of possibilities with which that
class can work
similarly we cannot walk
modifying a class that is already past
to production because
because because if that class is in a
productive environment and it's already being
used by different people and
different implementations those
modifications can have impacts
unwanted and put them in a situation
ok we made a change and we don't know why
what or what happened
then be careful with those changes
that's why we always talk about we add
code we do not modify because the
modifications have repercussions that
we will not always be able to measure because in
a project that is getting bigger
enlarging and enlarging it becomes
getting harder in that regard yeah
so we talk about a class should
be closed to be modified the
only reason why we should do
changes in that class is for obviously
correct mistakes because there are mistakes
we are going to commit there will always be
mistakes we will not be able to avoid
we can fly us on the flag of the
event development text we can do a
lot of things but we're still
human and we will make mistakes and if
are not technical errors can be
errors at the requirements level
then there is no escape from the
mistakes that's important to mark
in that sense
seems contradictory
that a class that we can modify only
the class under certain contradictions
and at the same time let us extend it
but
of course exactly as nobody says in the
comments are throwing out the idea that
keep it as a black box i have
than to assume that a class that is already
designed it's already implemented it has
have to function and in order to preserve that
behavior I need not get in
changes but build around that
in that sense yes
imagine let's draw a little bit
let's see if this works this will never
I did it live but today I feel daring
and authentic so
let's see what happens
let's imagine for a moment that we have
a function a class better said that
we are better we have a class
which is called shape or form
and we want for example this one that has
a function that
calculated
the area
as there are different ways to calculate the
area this will most likely not have
it has to be a class and it has to be
rather something like an interface because
each shape each geometric figure has
your way of expressing this example there
so let's replace here x
interface
just in case this seems like code but
it's closer to the pseudo code so
don't worry about mistakes
score or some minor detail is
simply by way of exemplifying
roughly the principles
then suppose that in that context
I have a rectangle class
and I also have a class nearby
each of these classes can
implement area calculation as you
correspond as convenient
so in this way we are
allowing the
functionality because we declare a
contract on a base way of working
without having to specify
how is the behavior for all
shapes imagine if I had
done this myself
in a single function
suppose instead of an interface
I would have proceeded with what was
point of writing it was to boot with
a safe class
and start defining a calculation method
of area
calculate edit area
with some parameters I don't know which ones
Imagine that I would have to be
asking is how
a rectangle for example
so
i do some of these things
is the shape a circle
and so with each of the themes
imagine there may be we have to
make one and for each shape
and this without scalable and we have to
keep modifying and pasting it
method all the time then we're going to
say this does not network does not continue open
cloud nor solid if we go to the case of
responsible design and sorry don't follow and
That boy
Let's say
while this one does
s me why
because we have the one unique
responsibility for each of the
implementations of the form
and we allow it to spread through
the different implementations
site abstraction concrete
how nice they were giving me the
blackboard i'm very happy with how
would that be ok let's continue
so
based on the example that we saw a good
class design allows to add
unedited code functionality
preexisting
because it is important to think about
interfaces
because when we create the classes
concrete just as we saw in the
fresh example
that's where we define functionality
but the interface defines us as it should
be that contract to that way of ordering
in what way are we going to work the
functionalities for each case
particular goes from the most general to
the most particular
and as a runner and it seems to me that
is also covered share it avoid
pre-existing code editing reduces
the risk of creating new errors
imagine all the times that too
we have to modify the function this of
Italy calculation by the mere fact that
I have to add a new shape all
We screw up we all put a finger of
more out there and we can inadvertently
make a change that basically ends
affecting we started playing the one
calculating the circle and inadvertently
we change the triangle formula and
bye we paste here the code that was
working because we are hand doing
both the same code base that
starts to cause problems in that
sense imagine two ways not
nothing happens with 20 and it can be a problem
Let's go then
talk about disk replacement
I want this to be translated for you
I want you to have it in these next few
minutes we are going to talk about the album
because it is literally that if it looks like
a duck quacks like a duck but
need batteries is probably
using the wrong drive and yes
not going to extend of a class
of a duck class if you want to use the
the same if you want to implement a control
remote for more than your remote control at 4
like a duck shouldn't do that the
idea yes
[Music]
each class that inherits from another we say
can be used as your father or mother
without knowing the differences
between them
what will these things mean so
axiomatic so so poetic also the
same time and follow all subclasses
they must operate within the behavior
expected of their base classes for more than
the specific functionality be
different this deserves blackboard
let's go down here
how to add a new one
it's okay
this is a classic of classics I have
one class
which is called list
which has among its various methods a
function
they receive and have no matter which
suppose you add to something that you
llama content
add an element that came and already
suppose we contain a vector in
javascript for example
talked about you know because it's language
that I have fresher but they can do
the exercise of transposing the concept into
any other language now the day of
Imagine tomorrow I come and say che
but I want to have a no list of
just read also then I say well
fantastic because i have a class
list that does everything I need
a list no more I need it to be from
read only then it occurs to me to do
a class ri 2 ri down est est ere
Spanish English to Nova Roy Down and List and
I say it extends
de list o de flour
but I don't want it to have the method of
add then what do I do
well I can grab define back
and throw a mistake
saying de cézanne around the est
this is a read-only list
on a scale of 1 to 10 how
more practice is this being a very
bad practice and 10 not at all
1 this is very bad practice because
because we are extending from one
abstraction that says add adds
whereas in the implementation that
we're adding we say it doesn't add
we are altering base behavior
of the class we are with
working and this is a problem this
breaks the scop principle because
because in this of which both the disc
morry down list deberían ser
interchangeable for any of the
functions that use it we're
breaking behavior then
he implementer of these elements does not
you will know the differences between
each one of these indies you're on
particular but they broke by breaking the
contract that means the am function
we are altering behavior if
you want a list to be just
read don't expose a function to not
do this rewrite it and leave it with
an error or
and the error is a solution a little bit
more decent than leaving it empty and not
do nothing because the mistake at least
you can capture it or do something
inform the developer
somehow
but notice how it's so simple what
and this on many sides I am sure
that the whole person who is also
seeing this at some point they saw something
like this somehow this is
more common than you think then
we don't have to alter behavior
of the abstractions in which we
we base
because if not what are we for
spreading of that abstraction and this
It also has a little to do with
It is
with something that we saw far above
we will see in 3d with segregation of
interfaces because we are exposing a
method that a wheel a list does not have
to have because it's read-only is
just then we are re
using the wrong extraction
good
let's continue what else do we have on
lisboa
just what we are talking about for
that a class is then a subtype in
terms of behavior must inherit
its members and operate within
limits of his original behavior
there they are saying on twitter to stay
saved well it will be saved
on our youtube channel it's there
Miguel, if you can do me the favor of
show the little sign of the east channel and
it's just telling me still for
extend the same method we can have
consider patterns like the template
method but conceptually extends and
does not change its nature there are patterns of
design that help us accommodate a little
this kind of thing is true is something that
could show you chat in another in another
encounter there is also an idea of
start talking a little bit more about
design patterns
this talk of solid comes exactly to
open the way to start these
discussions
so we say for a class to be
a subtype in terms of behavior
must inherit its members and operate
within the limits of your
original behavior if a subtype
does something the base class doesn't expect
is breaking this principle
only question if it would be correct if
round them up if you were the list parent in
this case
would not violate the principle would not break the
principle would be more correct but
semantically it would have to be revised
able to call it second list
class out there we could call it like
right evo ready something that indicates
that list if you can write but
if it would be more correct in terms of sun
it's very good very good observation
thanks doctor
alright another quick example going back to
geometric shapes
suppose we have this kind of
rectangle we have a member a
private property
with width and height and we have methods to
set width and height each
separately
we can have a discussion apart from
follow thesis etc is the best strategy
we can also discuss if it shouldn't
having a constructor is code from
example shouldn't be the focus now
suppose we define that a square
is an extension of a rectangle because
well it has four sides it has width and
high the square has the particularity
that width and height are always
equal then we say well give it
let's recompose to redefine the
set height function set height
and we're going to make it call the function
father or mother of being height and also
let's make her accept me
and if that were not or were not enough
to make it act also do what
same you set the height
half that makes a fuss with everything
this
if I will ask you why I violated the
disk replacement principle is going to
be from what we saw a while ago is
altering classroom behavior
orc rectangle is the base class
with which if it can be more
practical than implementing a square
do these little tricks but it's not clear no
it's obvious and your future and future self of
here makes a lot of time here
tell why this class is me
changing the stop when I say the
width that kind of decision is the one that
makes me see in time we have a
little bit of anger ourselves for not
document it or by making a decision to
design that's a little bit controversial
in this sense to solid is a big no
don't do this yes
imagine this can be transported
to much more complex systems where if
this happens the consequences are a
little bit more chaotic mixes in the case
of a good geometric figure a case
simple but think like this in a case
greater can be more complicated
we have this example and you also d
stealing a little java
is a stack class that the person who
was development let's imagine that we
they sent a pull request with this one
dust and quest with this code and this
we have grail list probe
and we use it to add and elements
and to remove and when we use in
our little program
we also have a clear function
and we say that this implementation
also breaks liskov because
because no structure structure of
stack we have a method that allows you
erase things the only thing you can do
is puig
it is just the beginning of a class
stack which is a stack then no
there should be this method which was
well but the point is that she
offered the functionality of adding and
remove with the arranger but
conceptually not supported
so how do we solve this problem
because it's ok
it's interesting to take advantage of a class to
that and reuse the behavior but
is this also how we are going to see in a
little while breaks interface segregation because
we are exposing a lot of methods
that do not correspond to the context of a
stack
now different would it be yes
instead of inheriting
composition
the biggest difference we have between
inheritance and composition is that
composition gives us more flexibility
because we inject the components that
we want to use and define the
behavior through the interface
of the class and we decide what
things we expose what we are
component hoisting and what not then
we can use an east rule that
for a release at this point we can
say yes but there are others
circumstances where it would not be
good idea we will see
It is
define it as as a component
protected or private depending on what
level of exposure and reuse
we want to achieve and if they look we can
keep adding and removing and the
clicker method is no longer on the interface
public then stop breaking the
disc replacement principle
why
we keep behaving again
correct and we go back to what
the abstraction we are using not
contradicts
the purpose of the class that we're
designing see what we are going to do
I want to stop here to check
this
all these comments from the beginning
what we are doing have to do with
how we design entities and
objects and functions with which
we work the code is anecdotal here
don't notice what it has to do with
a strategy of how we model the
entities and what do we want to do with
our code and how we have to
plan ahead so that we can
reuse and fail the code and that
last a little longer and not
we have to expose ourselves of those
situations from ok the code up to the
point to throw all not
let's not look for that is the modus
classic operandi let's not look for everything
time the answer is you have to throw
all overboard because it's a lot of
effort what we do and it's exhausting
make a blur and new account so
often if that's why we start presenting
these six these solution designs
to make our code more
more scalable resilient they start to
pop up all those magic little words
that now seem to us like smoke but
they end up being very good posts
responses to changing requirements and
requirements that have to scale in
time
I breathe this we go this principle of
interface segregation
we should read the person or the
consumer or the consumer of our
entities and our objects our
classes our functions what
need neither more nor less
we don't have to force expose
functions that don't go aren't going to
use this happened to us by example
that we just saw and with examples
previous of this one
depending on what things we want
Extending the example of the circle is that
We saw a little while ago for example if
and here the little word of
composition and as friend said is a
a little while to maintain the cohesion of
entities this principle of segregation
of interfaces proposes to decompose
non-cohesive interfaces on multiple
smaller interfaces and cisco de sivas
yes
the smaller the interface the more
its implementation is easy and
reuse
all these principles also point to
that the code in every structure
container be short concise short
specific and adhered to a purpose in
particular
we look for an interface a block of
code does not have 4000 lines
nobody wants to keep that
I don't know if they saw out there
there is a code block meme that
has a comment block that says
this code works well we don't know why
what and many like you have tried
deciphering what happens in this code you
We recommend that you don't, but if you
you get to touch this code update this
counter with the number of hours
you invested in this and the accountant said
like 193 hours
It is
nobody wants to read miles of code
we all want
tiny concrete things and
functional we seek that our life
easier working to the extent of
as possible and this principle also
accompany and help us on that side
if we have well defined interfaces
we can improve communication between
class and the entities that consume those
classes minimizing dependency
regarding members and where their use and
reducing the coupling this that
we talked at first the coupling it
it gets us everywhere and it's very
difficult in a productive system
undock things because you have to do
that the system coexists with the entities
you have to make the changes the
least disruptive possible and a job
surgical
which requires a lot of work on that
sense that requires a lot of effort
so if we can start
anticipate those efforts a lot
best
this principle always brings this
corollary it's not a it's not so obvious
from the start but it makes sense if
we start to think about it a little while
fewer classes share interfaces less
changes arise from the change in
an interface
and this makes the code more
sturdy
because we say this
imagine we have a class a
messaging message interface that you
deals with requesting and notifying different
things in an app in this case in
the payment application
you have internet you have methods to ask
a card report that the card is
invalid ask for a pin inform that the
pin is invalid to inform that the card
it has been denounced to request the data of
an account report that there is no
enough money in an account to report
that a lot of money was deposited and
report a balance
if you think about this it also breaks
the beginning of the century responsability the
to take sole responsibility because
because notice all the different things
what this interface is doing
the macro principle if you are to manage a
bank account for example but
managing a bank account is a
giant concept at the code level there's a
a lot of things that can happen there
let's talk if we need to add
functionalities then if we had
to implement for example different
management systems for different types
account
imagine that we are encapsulating
security financial issues
in the same entity
and if we have to make any changes
for example if we have to do a
I change the mechanism of starting
session that for example is in the method
to make Ping
we run the risk of impacting
methods that are related to the
Check the account balance value that
absolutely nothing to see then
what can be done to fix this
interface that clearly breaks the
segregation principle
we start breaking it down
notice now we have two interfaces
full month login and your gold
messenger while they do me
center deals with handling messaging
related to login or
account your web messenger deals with
whatever has to do with the
account withdrawal functionality
money in accounts for example
so it is very different how we handle
these interfaces and here we are precisely
offering the functionalities that
need and we are not exposing
methods that are not necessarily going to
use we don't bind as they said started to
the consuming entity of these
interfaces to that you use you have
exposed methods that will not require
nor will it be used because at the business level
at the level requirements are incompatible
and now investment principle of
dependency if he tells me and it's very
important are very important in this
presentation memes because they are
really descriptive
sun would you give a lamp directly to
electrical wiring on a wall I want
think that the answer that most
are you thinking is not for how much
risks that begs to function can
work saves but there's really what
better we can do
we say then in this principle that
a high-level module should not depend
of a low level module
this demands blackboard
let's go here and let's talk a
little bit of why we're saying what
what are we saying
yes microsoft deigned to these thanks
suppose I have an entity that
is a list we add I'm design the
system a school and I have a
entity
which is called students students list that
is a list of students
and since it is a list I say well
fantastic i'm going to extend
an array list why why not
and I can pass whatever is of type student
as if I were using the tip ado e
even what a nice definition of classes
how fantastic everything
What is the problem with this
this is high level
and this is low level
what if i have to change the
requirement of this class and suddenly
I need it to be a list that I use
some form of unique key
such as a hash map
I am forced to change this extension
sorry to change this extension and I'm going to
break anything you have to
consume a estradense list because I'm
changing the class from which it extends
so this is a bass extraction
level on which we should not depend
then there are several ways to get out of
this bind let's say but the easiest
is to think in composition
let's take
All this
let's define an interface in any case and
let's say inside there is a property
private called students and that
inside we decide
which is because we came up with a
realistic but it can be anything
you don't need to and out
and outward these changes we can
control
and for the rest of the exterior it will continue
being a study in shock this is not going to
matter what abstraction it derives from
because he is composing he is worked by
composition then we don't care
Really
then you have to be careful when
we make these extensions
because we go back to one of the
comfort symptoms begin to affect
begins to generate rigidity begins to
restrict the possibilities of our
code based a decision that's easy
to solve with another alternative
they are taking in this concept to do
we will work we will prefer in
based on the things solid suggests
maybe play a little more with
composition and keep this in mind this
of abstractions don't use a
low level extraction by impact
that it generates later when we want to do
changes
let's go back to where I have the most here
is the best
good
so what do we mean by this
which must depend on abstractions and the
abstractions that are clearly not the
low-level modules but any
interface or any element that
we need
and we go back to this we go from the general
to the particular an abstraction cannot
depend on particularities the
particularities should depend on the
abstraction in that sense
this is the super formal way and
academic to say what we just
see in that sense if the
particularities of abstraction
change the high-level module should not
being affected this reduces the
coupling and impact of changes to
design level and also allows testing
components in isolation
if you look this far with this
with the example that I just showed
I can change what kind of
list we use internally in our
dance list for example and it won't
import because it is component ized
and abstraction does not depend on
particularity just as we just
of doing
the question comes back then what
we should answer this sun would give a
lamp directly the electric cable
of a wall and not because there are ways of
avoid them just then this no
let's go to the most difficult in that sense
yes
good
I talked a lot I told them a lot of
things so
you are invited to join me and we are going to
hide the screen for a while because it's
much more super interesting and that's why it's
really what what I think about what
I put the last one started are things that the
at first they seem very tedious and not
makes us want to read or that there
you see a lot finding those examples of
code or specific things but they can
save your life sit for a while and
think it two seconds and say how
theory do what can save hours
programming when I see people out there
that that starts encoding input
don't sit down and make a good diagram
say well I should think about it if the sand
out there to program and this happens
it is also part of the
experience a little bit when you just
the times
you only realize
as our dear friend per se says
blood
there are people doing softbank auding
that they are shot to solve
the problem and people that as
the experience of time passes or not
because it is also a style of
programming is this you can start
prefer design solutions a little bit
rather than holding you back from analysis
that this is the most tedious part of
development and that few people
really like but look at all the
things that we can tackle by remembering
these five principles and notice that
these principles don't talk about code not
they talk about using
this way of writing this line of
literal code in this language
budget are not ways to organize
the code tells me santi for cockroach
that stamina ripped from metal
this this kind of thing can be applied
to any programming language in
any level of experience that
we have because it is more than a whole
change of mind regarding how
we analyze how we face a problem and
how we seek to solve it
what we are looking for in this is to start
produce higher quality code
make it more scalable than we can
easily maintain and not have to walk
relying on memory aids to
remember from here two months that we wanted
say when we write this or that
this helps us to make the code more
easy to understand just by yourself a
consequence that is implemented
these principles can have is to reduce
the amount of documentation you make
missing because you know this combined with a
principle of naming things right
undock well component izar and also
all this helps the code to
express for yourself and that the person
read it requires little and no
contextualization of why certain
things more than beyond what
corresponds to understand the product of
business itself of course not that
always have to explain it a
little bit more but design decisions
coupled to that
they should start to come off a little bit
more naturally apart whether they have it or not
as fair as a comment to make
not only serves for maintenance
of for oneself and to maintain oneself for
What a nation in the dark the day
time to modify water but
also works for your team or
when we have teams and we start to
make the modules a little independent well
you work on something I work on
something else and when you have to
offer you an interface with a certain
functionality that the other is thinking
how you did it or what other
functions has but to try to give you what
what it should be and in parts that
understand girls easy to use and
people have to get into the
code to see what you will use is not the
only one is asking if it makes shelf
one shot is worth applying solid
for something that may have little time to
life as well as can climb
very much
I dare say yes
depending on the time of the invitation
generally the entities for a product
it can become ephemeral capable
this but such with this point of
scalable and worth applying
principles out there more than all
for doing practice because this is a
habit to develop think about
solidity something you have to practice it
but I keep thinking around there too
It is
it's not such a big effort that
you have to do
but it is to generate the habit of doing
pause before you start writing the
code even if I draw as I am
doing me on the board today this and see
Let's see
is this the best way to solve the
problem is in asking the question the
rest over time practice the
experience comes alone but I think what
the harder it is to pause before
of sitting down writing code like everyone
we like this but ask me questions
seems more is the most important thing up
maybe it's a good starting point as
to start facing this whole issue of
patterns of applying sun and others already at
less for what you see and if
they ask there is it worth applying
when they get into the habit you are not going to
ask that because you are going to apply
because it comes out directly start
already work that way because it's you
shape is your habit is the way that
you build software knowing that the
tomorrow I upload that same in beat
and they can use it for something
big they copy it what it does and
it works then it's the custom it's
start working this way
through questions further back guys
know good online resources type
freak or similar fields that allows
implement this to go
incorporating it into the day to day
there are a lot of resources that are
hanging around for this topic
in the link of the youtube video when
came out this is going to be a
I am going to add in addition to the
description of some more little things I will
leave a couple of useful links there that
can use as a reference
this in principle if you google
main suns there are plenty of
respect material to read more
depth
but if there is totally there is material in
that sense there is persistent I don't know
the truth
I don't know if even on YouTube there are many
things too many videos
it's a matter of reading a little here
over there and take a little bit out of each side and
only weapons of the concept me for example
my particular case agreed to me they touched me
study patterns at the time and want
not seeing or not studying them wikipedia
it seems crazy to me and yes because wikipedia
and wikipedia were well explained and
the way to practice them was to do
small pieces of concrete code
until they grab the knack let's say 7
incorporates frank question
in addition to such scripts and others
tools can help us to
apply these concepts the modeling
there's a topic with this question that's
very comfortable which is the bran
one of the things that more than more
marketing in the talk is that it transcends
script languages ​​itself
the only thing it adds to you is the question of
you pdo
if all the conceptual analysis for
apply the principles and you can also
explain with work so you
I assure and exactly of the articles
that I will leave as a reference are from
how to implement it particularly in
javascript because I don't know why if it's
by the multi paradigmatic nature
of language or because she goes
simply and a half that no one
that's why it kind of seems like
ser front end
own which front-end has a lot
difficulty incorporating this concept
conditioned but pediment of different
not in a different stand
long ago it is an environment where
we work there are no distinctions in that
sense this I even think there was something
you had to see an article a
time that showed how in riad you can
use solid principles there
ways of transporting it perfectly
to the context that we can use what
important here is
when designing the entities or by
example if I have to create a service or
a class in some framework that
use for example I'm going to stay with
the example of xavestre because it moves away
of the question is to start wondering
ok if i have to design a service
then I have to reuse parts of
that service no layers layers I can
break it down into smaller services
for example this if I have to work
with age types with structure of
data that I'm going to have to be
using i'm making the best
abstractions that I can are the shapes
easier to organize or I'm
exposing a lot of elements that the
implementation are not going to be used in
actually those are the questions that go
to be thinks let's think of solid as a
sort of checklist of questions that
we have to ask ourselves when
work and apply the design of
these entities
so much that kinda relates to the one
always intersects with these principles
but they cost there to unite all the
pieces
kinda the same thing we always say no
little by little you will catch the habit no
I mean that in one in one
same piece of code is going to incorporate
all the concepts in the world so that
I know that you will always have a little more
of one a little more of another the same with
the theme of high collection and bass
compliance that is to what extent is
well the low coupling up to what
point is good the high correction is
something about the size of the software that
you are going to create also remember that
you can have very very very low
compliance but perhaps the complexity
of the software will grow in terms of
number of pieces of file code
Whatever
there is a very blurred line and a half and
let's say you have to consider but
here and that line is determined by the
criteria and from the experience that
let's incorporate in this sense
what a good question the one that just
do
I am from programming oriented
objects or can be applied applicable
on other paradigms and is based on
principle in the paradigm oriented
objects but there are concepts that can
for example, to transpose the paradigm of
functional programming
It is
specifically on the composition side
and by how do you extend this
it makes sense to think about it from that side
although it is more than everything designed to
object events and this can be
applicable perhaps not all principles
maybe some more than others but yes
should be able to after putting others
paradigms if we are a little thing that
I stay where you turn this
just like with design patterns
which is a topic that we are going to start
touch in next videos in next
transmissions let's think there is always
a traitor there is always something we give up
some concession that we make for by
favor certain aspects of the code not
we can have 100% of things
working with all the principles and
all nice because there is just
principles that at some point collide
each other based on the requirements of
business and let's not forget that
we write codes because we work on
that then we can have everything
technical purist we want but no
you have to forget that there is a project and
a motivation and a purpose for the
which one we are writing the code not
we write codes because it's for
write code or yes but the idea is that
let's not lose the axis of that concept
yes because I think that out there is fine
maintain all good practices and
all the patterns that you can always
and when they don't go away from you
ask why you're going to end up working you
you lose hours and budget and everything
let's say for work it wasn't
necessary to leave the idea is that this we
save time not to save time
extra
to another question I saw
when you come in morgan and if you give
note that in each block you have a
rat as he recommends is to start to
have good practices and befriend
design patterns and apply get out
in one let's say yes yes
is to start thinking about how to
reproduce how to rethink the
same problem you are trying to solve
from another perspective
Now there are many times that I think
all must have passed us all
people who are here we have
past we've had to develop
a form of whatever
forms are everywhere
how many times have we ever redesigned me
they pass career for example I must
have designed six systems
generation of forms together with
dynamic fields
and I guarantee that I added to all
something or get something out of it because of repeating
exercise makes you rethink your
analysis of the problem you chords you
deny with this before and that's a
problem then I'm going to change the
behavior
but there are a lot of things that
as we practice on that
practice practice practice befriend
with design patterns not knowing
those by heart but to know where
context serve us there are very
taken to learn this
to learn about design patterns to
see if I can quickly find the one
I know while you're looking for truth he doesn't
just befriend the sun and the
patterns but what we were saying about
Well friend, take your time
stop don't lengthen the keys and five and
seven a doodle cartoonist the class
see how you should do it
or what happens to me for wii me a
little bit I started doing these start to
write when something comes up that
I had not diagrammed it and there were already two
times it was the same when
there it was the second time they came
doing the exact same thing was braking
and so it doesn't stop I could follow it and
finish it already or I'm going and pulled it the
abstraction it has to be I think so
accordingly and then continue to
end is a certain saving hours
later because I surely forget
again that block and already had it solved
so out there that's ours
exercise taking time not
observed
it's easy to follow and continue a code and
finish it but if you know it will bring
back to zero gradually to
cantoblanco colors shot very good
ask when refactoring
he clearly wasn't tired of this
way is it feasible to apply solid this
would mean having to discard everything
what is already done
I am a supporter of migrations
progressive and
just reborn the one out so
can be based on ldl principles
isco to replace parts as
we are implementing we can go
replacing component by component
applying the principles of solidity to
man was that the main class the
classes the components not yet
are my degrees can you follow
running on the basis of bits of
code that we are replacing
in that sense it seems super to me
workable to apply on but it's a job
gradual we can't claim to do it in
a pull request all together because no no
is that going to work
ok so this component by
components can be applied alone
definitely
meanwhile I tell you that there was
turned this page very very broadcast on
this site
ree factoring a guru point has a
lots of material regarding the clinician to
solid and design patterns to everything and is
super super concrete is very cool for
read I have been using it in the laburo
pretty and this is very nice and helps
a lot to investigate a little more about
I didn't have this topic then so
surely clean a glance ávila
share recently and they are very cute
here please also comment reading working
in effective and draw new and code
didn't know him
the law above some things there is a
lot of strategies that have to do
with the legal code so to do
migrations just at work I
I am in the process of a migration that
is getting quite long this and the
strategy that we are adopting
basically this is what we told you
just frank is a component to the
You see a little step at the same time that nothing explodes
that everything keeps going somehow
mysterious
the mysterious no but out
it seems that if this one basically
trying to limit the area of
intervention as much as possible is
important especially in these things of
work with legacy and trans code in
transferring it a new code is super
super important to have a good
survey of what is the area of
intervention have super detailed
what are the steps and stages in
that this migration will take place and
good planning to make it
controllable
because it also has to be realistic in
that sense if we want to migrate a base
of giant code that 10 years ago
He has problems
you have to be ordered in that process
totally
there are a lot of books dedicated to
subject that punctually is one of those
more I recommend to start
mais I have enough material in this
theme for a lot of things people
dear there are already a lot of materials
there and little is said about these things
talk a lot about framework talk a lot
technology there is a lot of talk about how
solve problem x with tools
but few tools are given that
have to do with the problems of
design of code solutions that by
after all it is the root of all
other problems then
it's good to start thinking more about
analytical modeling we all like
be in the area typing on the keyboard
wildly as if there was no
tomorrow but notice how long we
we would save and we could write things
that we really enjoy a little more
At least I know we dedicate so much
time we think not on that side
let's write code nice code that we
like it and this tool helps in a
lot for that and that people with
the ones that work and even you
themselves in the future they will thank and
they will thank other people
have these considerations in that of
mother a little crazy to say but I mean
many or all or almost all
frameworks we work with
we know the language that apply
these concepts god
and the good thing is that when you go
grabbing the practice you give yourself
realize how it is that applies everything
since when what if I when you see the
class structure of a framework
visual for him I remember I started to
know when I started studying already
swing in time to make
graphical interfaces and suddenly I started
to see a number of patterns that
applied for windows extension
component buttons how to separate the
behaviors like components did
action on such or such and you start to
account on these things and really
how can you improve or change a
framework
knowing these concepts
there are similar alternatives to solid
solidity as the best and only way out as well
as well as there are thousands of frameworks and
hundreds of programming language there
hundreds of principles and good practices
also available solidity what I
know and the one that I've done tried to
implement I'm still
learning there are things that I still of
solid the one that costs me the most is the one
always as we can with a colleague in the
I work the one that costs me the most is the
dependency inversion because I think
injection instead of investment and I'm already
does a machete on the head
basically but but yeah
there are alternatives if you ask me what
I gave you now concrete well I don't know
it happens but but I do know there are
nobody because they must have concepts
similar yes yes names can
be different the focus can be
different and at some point it will
come together will know all the idioms
totally if you're pulling there
also something very cool that is very
it is a balance
it's also a balance sheet and you're going
finding for example driver software
donde peter shows versos writer briefing
swayze if there is like everything scales is what
that we were talking about a while ago with
design patterns the same goes for
there is always a trade off if not
we are finding what is the
downside of what we're doing
means that we are not
wondering enough what is it
what we are doing and we are being
finishing the turtle is safe out there
is yes
nothing at all is magic there is no plan no
there are silver vouchers in this there is no
prophetic recipes that save us no no
there are no tools solve every
one with their reach what they can and
it also depends on how we do them
we can use a hammer for everything if
we want to use a hammer for everything and not
I know if it's real, it's real and it's funny to me
yes indeed when we start to see how
this relates to some
some development styles like by
example this 20 and see it pent and if solid
it starts to make more sense when
I started to compose ok redundancies there
speaking of composition because it has to
give a make it up someplace
point
solid the clean code are all things that
complement each other and form a base
super cute code in that regard
it seems bureaucratic and tedious
like few things in life at the beginning
but when you find the love in
against finding the benefits and you
starts to work because
it seems something else
you should not be afraid to formalize
how we work in the code
and that applies to all languages ​​and
walk everyone you have to make a switch
very big with 20 keys and it comes out
necessary
and that's going to be the first pattern of
design let's see how to fix that
there are cases so they are super common in
that sense
and that we do it every so often by talking and
there among other very important things
also when we start working with
code and this also merits talks
separated
this if daniel this comment goes up
we want to use a hammer for everyone
but we shouldn't totally not
we should do and we can even
and asia
a is full of stories of people
developers who in production have
done complicated things the good factor and
nothing beats him and there's a lot of those good
oh blue cheese good patterns this is
a miracle moment they had come together
very similar things in terms of
projects that acting had a good factor
and it was my good singleton for everyone
century and it is spectacular and it served me
influenced to scam well there are those who
will say that this pardon does not apply
as a design pattern there is no pattern and
medium yes but as such
hold the 300 line switches
code yeah yeah sure but after
break the rule after fixing
alright well we're close to closing you
it seems that we make the announcements of all
of all our beautiful encounters
and we come with the goats and it's the part
of the goats good first of all
so thank you all for coming
watching the talks they had a lot of people
interacting today asking questions
I hope you have served something
remember that these videos always
you can see on our youtube channel
on YouTube bars bars elbow now
we have the little name after a lot
hours since video we have the channel
quoted yes yes yes because here you are
questions with the tapped before before
finish the chivas but I have to say
only redex exists there is no
answer is yes to everything and well thanks
remember there is on our channel
youtube the videos will be so much
this one like all the previous ones
surely everyone who comes too
need it seems me today but let's think
in making a playlist for
different themes we already have in fact
and try like this if there is a grandpa who is
broadcast is going to be on that playlist
we have finds lamb is divided
tells you in three areas we have the
lands of online education which are the
that we have been doing most of the
time the entrepreneurial talks
that we started a little while ago and the talks
from haiti who are the ones we are half
loading now with this space plus a
our previous lists that already
we had everyone have their playlist so
they can go up there all the
events that we are having out there
how to increase the ones that come is a
excellent question the easiest
apart from following us in all our
networks we have instagram twitter
facebook and linkedin and youtube and everything is
activate the bell activate the bell
also if we don't know this for the other
bernake we did that to him even
if you go to this address I will
pasar code
bright dot com have a little button
continue with the one that will be integrated
automatically every time we post
a new event we all our
talks to know more or less what
turnout we wait and how many people are going
to come and what interest is there in certain
fear all our talks although
then some we make them public
we make them go through the event bright of
this way we are warning I chose
to those who subscribe to our profile
organizer every time we post
an event they will find out
automatically exactly of all
ways try to always stay on
twitter y twitter instagram facebook
linkedin everywhere and always
we make publications of all
events we do
and we are making them
follow-up we are commenting so
they will always always see the
event comments also includes
activate the like bell and
subscribe be from the youtube channel because
will always notify you when with
anticipation when we start one of the
talks because they usually come
those scheduled to start good
winter atmosphere this comfort but
they are always programmed narrating that
a day in advance so yes yes already
they go in there you are notifying them with
time this case of networks are going to
find out easy so in that they will not
never grab
ortemán for that and I forgot it was like that
but always also to our website
org point necklace they will find a
calendar so giant with all the
events that take place in the month and not
only those that are made by
necklace but we also put
constantly events that give other
communities
either in workshops in meetup talks
we post them there to go
integrating participate equally go
knowing more about these communities and
more people no I don't know if I forget something else
that we are seeing the most part
important so good the broken homeland
remember this is an open space
is available to all those who
want to come and offer to give a
talk to offer a theme of
again by the same networks they put a
comment send us a little message me
would like to see on this topic learn
about this for suddenly if they would like
give some talk they can also
do through other networks
and we are also looking there
there is the link
can enter something is a simple
form a complete in some
questions mark some cjex a
little description of what you can
listen to it and well after that
we coordinate to make a call
talk a little more about it and coordinate
a date the idea of ​​this is that they can
share either a technology a
methodology some experience of yours or
something you feel you can contribute to the
community and you can help let's say to
all that is in this case the
software development or if you want
apply for some of the others
categories like undertaking one and it
can do but the is not open
space for everyone so take heart
run and now what we
we organize
a space for this and lastly as
always current discord we are
organizing all these talks workshops
and others to work and effort of
all its members and all the support
that we also have from the community as well
not now
we are currently receiving
donations through our portal
code air dot org is going to win and apart
we have to place also there is the
on-screen link for those who
want to contribute money in some way
way with coder everything you enter
we are currently using it for
improve our infrastructure power
improve the talks offer you more
quality that has more pretty things
greater willingness lends so from
already thank you very much to all those who already
contributed and what they are contributing with
let's continually say love heart
and he who cannot do brings a
monetary donation there is always the
possibility to go directly to the button
from the like retweet where he shares and I
I think of being the biggest part
can you give us today is totally
break it and nothing that people find out and
that people or propose talks or anything
we are always there listening
watching reading everything so well
please cheer up because this day there
more things more pages more risks good
we are growing little by little
nothing like I said I started to come more
Haitian talks so be there
attentive yes yes and propose that
sure we found someone to
give it
great thank you very much to all
people who joined us in
this talk live thanks to those who
are watching to read the recorded version and
well stay tuned and stay tuned
and see you in the next edition of
find cover thank you very much everyone
like and bye bye
[Music]